Guide to the Ray Family Papers 1794 - 1889 MS 513
New-York Historical Society
Ray Family Papers
1794-1889
New-York Historical Society
MS 513
0.75 Linear feet (2 boxes)
The Ray Family was a prominent New York City family in the nineteenth century. Family members include Cornelius Ray (1755-1827), Robert Ray (1794-1879), Richard Ray (1799-1836) and Robert Ray Hamilton (1851-1890), the great grandson of Alexander Hamilton and primary member of the family featured in this collection. The majority of the materials concern a scandal Hamilton was the victim of, between August and November 1889, when a woman named Evangeline (Eva) Mann falsely led him to believe he was the father of a baby, Beatrice, who she had reportedly purchased from a midwife.
Biographical / Historical
The Ray Family was a prominent New York City family in the nineteenth century. Family members include Cornelius Ray (1755-1827), Robert Ray (1794-1879), Richard Ray (1799-1836) and Robert Ray Hamilton (1851-1890), the great grandson of Alexander Hamilton and primary member of the family featured in this collection.
Robert Ray Hamilton was born in New York City on March 18, 1851 to Schuyler Hamilton and Cornelia Ray and attended Columbia College and Law School. He practiced law for a few years and then discovered an interest in politics. Hamilton was elected a member of Legislature from 1887-89 and served as the Republican Assemblyman in the eleventh district in 1881 and from 1886-88.
In the mid-1880s Hamilton began an unfortunate relationship with Evangeline (Eva) Mann, which resulted in a scandal that captivated public attention for months. Hamilton secretly married her in January 1889 after she convinced him that he had fathered a baby, Beatrice, who she had reportedly purchased from a midwife. In August of that year Hamilton discovered that not only had Eva lied to him about Beatrice, but that she was still reportedly married to another man, Joshua Mann. During an argument about Mann, Eva attempted to attack Hamilton with a knife; however, failing to hit him, she turned her attack on a maid, Mary Donnelly, who she suspected of telling Hamilton the truth about Beatrice and Mann. As punishment for stabbing and nearly killing Mary, Eva was sentenced in September 1889 to two years in the state prison in Trenton, NJ. By October Hamilton began the process of having his marriage with Eva annulled.
In May 1890 Hamilton left New York to take part in a hunting trip in the West. However, he soon made headlines again when he was found drowned in Yellowstone National Park's Snake River that September.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following two series. Within these series materials are organized alphabetically and then chonologically. In the case that an item was undated, it was placed at the end of all similar, dated items.
Missing Title
Series I: Ray Family
Series II: Robert Ray Hamilton
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Custodial History
Donated to the New-York Historical Society by Albert Paradis in 1980.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, deeds and business records from the Ray Family, primarily belonging to or concerning Robert Ray Hamilton, the great grandson of Alexander Hamilton. The majority of the materials date from a four month period in 1889 following a scandal involving Robert Ray Hamilton and Evangeline (Eva) Mann, a woman he secretly married after she falsely led him to believe that he was the father of a baby, Beatrice, who she had reportedly purchased from a midwife.
Correspondence.; Deeds.; Scandals -- United States.; New York (N.Y.); Foundlings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Subpoenas; Telegrams.; Ray, Robert, 1794-1879; Ray, Richard, 1799-1836; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804; Hamilton, Robert Ray, 1851-1890; Ray, Cornelius, 1755-1827; Hamilton, Schuyler, 1822-1903
- Series I: Ray Family
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials including deeds, bills, estate and account statements and notes pertaining to various members of the Ray Family, including Cornelius Ray, Robert Ray, Schuyler Hamilton, Schuyler Hamilton, Jr., Robert Ray Hamilton, Nathalie Baylies and Richard King.
  - Cornelius Ray, Business Papers, 1794-1833 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Deeds, 1825-37 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Deeds and Business Papers, 1844-56 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Deeds and Business Papers, 1868-82, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Estate of Robert Ray, Vouchers and Drafts, 1880-84 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Tax Bills, 1832-52 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series II: Robert Ray Hamilton
  This series contains materials pertaining to Robert Ray Hamilton. The majority of the materials concern a scandal Hamilton was the victim of, between August and November 1889, when a woman named Evangeline (Eva) Mann falsely led him to believe he was the father of a baby, Beatrice, who she had reportedly purchased from a midwife. Only months after Hamilton secretly married her because of this claim, the truth of the situation was released publicly, resulting in family, friends and the public sending telegrams and writing letters to Hamilton expressing their sympathy for him, outrage at the situation and/or interest in adopting Beatrice. In addition to the correspondence regarding the scandal is the subpoena directing Hamilton to appear in court for Eva's trial, held in September 1889. This series also contains business correspondence regarding Hamilton's work as a lawyer and real estate agent, as well as bills resulting from his efforts to furnish the Republican Headquarters in New York City.
  - Bills for Furnishing the Republican Headquarters, 1888-89 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Business Correspondence, 1868-89 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence from Family, Aug. - Nov. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence from Friends, Aug. - Nov. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence from the Public, Aug. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence from the Public, Sept. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence from the Public, Sept. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence from the Public, Oct. - Nov. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence from the Public, 1889, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Subpoena, Sept. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Telegrams, Aug. - Oct. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 14)